CHAPTER XIX.
THE next day opened a new scene at Longbourn. Mr. Collins made his declaration in form. Having
resolved to do it without loss of time, as his leave of absence extended only to the following
Saturday, and having no feelings of diffidence to make it distressing to himself even at the moment,
he set about it in a very orderly manner, with all the observances which he supposed
a regular part of the business. On finding Mrs. Bennet, Elizabeth, and one of the younger
girls together, soon after breakfast, he addressed the mother in these words,—
“May I hope, madam, for your interest with your fair daughter Elizabeth,
when I solicit for the honour of a private audience with her in the course of this morning?”
Before Elizabeth had time for anything but a blush of surprise, Mrs. Bennet instantly answered,—
“Oh dear! Yes, certainly. I am sure Lizzy will be very happy—I am sure she can have no
objection. Come, Kitty, I want you upstairs.” And gathering her work together, she was
hastening away, when Elizabeth called out,— “Dear ma’am, do not go. I beg you will not
go. Mr. Collins must excuse me. He can have nothing to say to me that anybody
need not hear. I am going away myself.” “No, no, nonsense, Lizzy. I desire you
will stay where you are.” And upon Elizabeth’s seeming really, with vexed and embarrassed looks,
about to escape, she added, “Lizzy, I insist upon your staying and hearing Mr. Collins.”
Elizabeth would not oppose such an injunction; and a moment’s consideration making her also sensible
that it would be wisest to get it over as soon and as quietly as possible, she sat down again,
and tried to conceal, by incessant employment, the feelings which were divided between distress
and diversion. Mrs. Bennet and Kitty walked off, and as soon as they were gone, Mr. Collins began,—
“Believe me, my dear Miss Elizabeth, that your modesty, so far from doing you any disservice,
rather adds to your other perfections. You would have been less amiable in my eyes had there not
been this little unwillingness; but allow me to assure you that I have your respected mother’s
permission for this address. You can hardly doubt the purport of my discourse, however
your natural delicacy may lead you to dissemble; my attentions have been too marked to be mistaken.
Almost as soon as I entered the house I singled you out as the companion of my future life.
But before I am run away with by my feelings on this subject, perhaps it will be advisable for me
to state my reasons for marrying—and, moreover, for coming into Hertfordshire with the design
of selecting a wife, as I certainly did.” The idea of Mr. Collins, with all his solemn
composure, being run away with by his feelings, made Elizabeth so near laughing that she could
not use the short pause he allowed in any attempt to stop him farther, and he continued,—
“My reasons for marrying are, first, that I think it a right thing for every clergyman in
easy circumstances (like myself) to set the example of matrimony in his parish;
secondly, that I am convinced it will add very greatly to my happiness; and,
thirdly, which perhaps I ought to have mentioned earlier, that it is the particular advice and
recommendation of the very noble lady whom I have the honour of calling patroness. Twice has she
condescended to give me her opinion (unasked too!) on this subject; and it was but the very Saturday
night before I left Hunsford,—between our pools at quadrille, while Mrs. Jenkinson was arranging
Miss De Bourgh’s footstool,—that she said, ‘Mr. Collins, you must marry. A clergyman like you must
marry. Choose properly, choose a gentlewoman for my sake, and for your own; let her be an active,
useful sort of person, not brought up high, but able to make a small income go a good way. This
is my advice. Find such a woman as soon as you can, bring her to Hunsford, and I will visit her.’
Allow me, by the way, to observe, my fair cousin, that I do not reckon the notice and kindness of
Lady Catherine de Bourgh as among the least of the advantages in my power to offer. You will find her
manners beyond anything I can describe; and your wit and vivacity, I think, must be acceptable
to her, especially when tempered with the silence and respect which her rank will inevitably excite.
Thus much for my general intention in favour of matrimony; it remains to be told why my
views were directed to Longbourn instead of my own neighbourhood, where I assure you there are many
amiable young women. But the fact is, that being, as I am, to inherit this estate after the death
of your honoured father (who, however, may live many years longer), I could not satisfy myself
without resolving to choose a wife from among his daughters, that the loss to them might be as
little as possible when the melancholy event takes place—which, however, as I have already said,
may not be for several years. This has been my motive, my fair cousin, and I flatter myself
it will not sink me in your esteem. And now nothing remains for me but to assure you in
the most animated language of the violence of my affection. To fortune I am perfectly indifferent,
and shall make no demand of that nature on your father, since I am well aware that it could not
be complied with; and that one thousand pounds in the 4 per cents., which will not be yours
till after your mother’s decease, is all that you may ever be entitled to. On that head,
therefore, I shall be uniformly silent: and you may assure yourself that no ungenerous reproach
shall ever pass my lips when we are married.” It was absolutely necessary to interrupt him now.
“You are too hasty, sir,” she cried. “You forget that I have made no answer. Let me
do it without further loss of time. Accept my thanks for the compliment you are paying
me. I am very sensible of the honour of your proposals, but it is impossible
for me to do otherwise than decline them.” “I am not now to learn,” replied Mr. Collins,
with a formal wave of the hand, “that it is usual with young ladies to reject the
addresses of the man whom they secretly mean to accept, when he first applies for their favour;
and that sometimes the refusal is repeated a second or even a third time. I am, therefore, by
no means discouraged by what you have just said, and shall hope to lead you to the altar ere long.”
“Upon my word, sir,” cried Elizabeth, “your hope is rather an extraordinary one after
my declaration. I do assure you that I am not one of those young ladies (if such young ladies there
are) who are so daring as to risk their happiness on the chance of being asked a second time. I am
perfectly serious in my refusal. You could not make me happy, and I am convinced that I am the
last woman in the world who would make you so. Nay, were your friend Lady Catherine to know me,
I am persuaded she would find me in every respect ill qualified for the situation.”
“Were it certain that Lady Catherine would think so,” said Mr. Collins, very gravely—“but I cannot
imagine that her Ladyship would at all disapprove of you. And you may be certain that when I
have the honour of seeing her again I shall speak in the highest terms of your modesty,
economy, and other amiable qualifications.” “Indeed, Mr. Collins, all praise of me will
be unnecessary. You must give me leave to judge for myself, and pay me the compliment of believing
what I say. I wish you very happy and very rich, and by refusing your hand, do all in my power to
prevent your being otherwise. In making me the offer, you must have satisfied the delicacy of
your feelings with regard to my family, and may take possession of Longbourn estate whenever it
falls, without any self-reproach. This matter may be considered, therefore, as finally settled.” And
rising as she thus spoke, she would have quitted the room, had not Mr. Collins thus addressed her,—
“When I do myself the honour of speaking to you next on the subject,
I shall hope to receive a more favourable answer than you have now given me; though I am far from
accusing you of cruelty at present, because I know it to be the established custom of your
sex to reject a man on the first application, and, perhaps, you have even now said as much to
encourage my suit as would be consistent with the true delicacy of the female character.”
“Really, Mr. Collins,” cried Elizabeth, with some warmth, “you puzzle me exceedingly. If
what I have hitherto said can appear to you in the form of encouragement,
I know not how to express my refusal in such a way as may convince you of its being one.”
“You must give me leave to flatter myself, my dear cousin, that your refusal of my addresses are
merely words of course. My reasons for believing it are briefly these:—It does not appear to me
that my hand is unworthy your acceptance, or that the establishment I can offer would be any other
than highly desirable. My situation in life, my connections with the family of De Bourgh,
and my relationship to your own, are circumstances highly in my favour;
and you should take it into further consideration that, in spite of your manifold attractions,
it is by no means certain that another offer of marriage may ever be made you. Your portion is
unhappily so small, that it will in all likelihood undo the effects of your loveliness and amiable
qualifications. As I must, therefore, conclude that you are not serious in your rejection of me,
I shall choose to attribute it to your wish of increasing my love by suspense, according
to the usual practice of elegant females.” “I do assure you, sir, that I have no pretensions
whatever to that kind of elegance which consists in tormenting a respectable man. I would rather be
paid the compliment of being believed sincere. I thank you again and again for the honour you
have done me in your proposals, but to accept them is absolutely impossible. My feelings in
every respect forbid it. Can I speak plainer? Do not consider me now as an elegant female
intending to plague you, but as a rational creature speaking the truth from her heart.”
“You are uniformly charming!” cried he, with an air of awkward gallantry;
“and I am persuaded that, when sanctioned by the express authority of both your excellent parents,
my proposals will not fail of being acceptable.” To such perseverance in wilful self-deception
Elizabeth would make no reply, and immediately and in silence withdrew; determined, that if he
persisted in considering her repeated refusals as flattering encouragement, to apply to her father,
whose negative might be uttered in such a manner as must be decisive, and whose
behaviour at least could not be mistaken for the affectation and coquetry of an elegant female.
CHAPTER XX.
MR. COLLINS was not left long to the silent contemplation of his successful love; for Mrs.
Bennet, having dawdled about in the vestibule to watch for the end of the conference, no sooner saw
Elizabeth open the door and with quick step pass her towards the staircase, than she entered the
breakfast-room, and congratulated both him and herself in warm terms on the happy prospect of
their nearer connection. Mr. Collins received and returned these felicitations with equal pleasure,
and then proceeded to relate the particulars of their interview, with the result of which
he trusted he had every reason to be satisfied, since the refusal which his cousin had steadfastly
given him would naturally flow from her bashful modesty and the genuine delicacy of her character.
This information, however, startled Mrs. Bennet: she would have been glad to be equally satisfied
that her daughter had meant to encourage him by protesting against his proposals, but she dared
not believe it, and could not help saying so. “But depend upon it, Mr. Collins,” she added,
“that Lizzy shall be brought to reason. I will speak to her about it myself directly. She is a
very headstrong, foolish girl, and does not know her own interest; but I will make her know it.”
“Pardon me for interrupting you, madam,” cried Mr. Collins; “but if she is really headstrong and
foolish, I know not whether she would altogether be a very desirable wife to a man in my situation,
who naturally looks for happiness in the marriage state. If, therefore, she actually
persists in rejecting my suit, perhaps it were better not to force her into accepting me,
because, if liable to such defects of temper, she could not contribute much to my felicity.”
“Sir, you quite misunderstand me,” said Mrs. Bennet, alarmed. “Lizzy is only headstrong
in such matters as these. In everything else she is as good-natured a girl as ever lived. I
will go directly to Mr. Bennet, and we shall very soon settle it with her, I am sure.”
She would not give him time to reply, but hurrying instantly to her husband,
called out, as she entered the library,— “Oh, Mr. Bennet, you are wanted immediately;
we are all in an uproar. You must come and make Lizzy marry Mr. Collins, for she vows she will
not have him; and if you do not make haste he will change his mind and not have her.”
Mr. Bennet raised his eyes from his book as she entered, and fixed them on her face
with a calm unconcern, which was not in the least altered by her communication.
“I have not the pleasure of understanding you,” said he, when she had finished
her speech. “Of what are you talking?” “Of Mr. Collins and Lizzy. Lizzy declares
she will not have Mr. Collins, and Mr. Collins begins to say that he will not have Lizzy.”
“And what am I to do on the occasion? It seems a hopeless business.”
“Speak to Lizzy about it yourself. Tell her that you insist upon her marrying him.”
“Let her be called down. She shall hear my opinion.”
Mrs. Bennet rang the bell, and Miss Elizabeth was summoned to the library.
“Come here, child,” cried her father as she appeared. “I have sent for you on an affair
of importance. I understand that Mr. Collins has made you an offer of marriage. Is it true?”
Elizabeth replied that it was. “Very well—and this offer of marriage
you have refused?” “I have, sir.”
“Very well. We now come to the point. Your mother insists upon your accepting
it. Is it not so, Mrs. Bennet?” “Yes, or I will never see her again.”
“An unhappy alternative is before you, Elizabeth. From this day you
must be a stranger to one of your parents. Your mother will never see
you again if you do not marry Mr. Collins, and I will never see you again if you do.”
Elizabeth could not but smile at such a conclusion of such a beginning;
but Mrs. Bennet, who had persuaded herself that her husband regarded the affair as she wished,
was excessively disappointed. “What do you mean,
Mr. Bennet, by talking in this way? You promised me to insist upon her marrying him.”
“My dear,” replied her husband, “I have two small favours to request. First,
that you will allow me the free use of my understanding on the present occasion;
and, secondly, of my room. I shall be glad to have the library to myself as soon as may be.”
Not yet, however, in spite of her disappointment in her husband, did Mrs. Bennet give up the point.
She talked to Elizabeth again and again; coaxed and threatened her by turns. She endeavoured to
secure Jane in her interest, but Jane, with all possible mildness, declined interfering;
and Elizabeth, sometimes with real earnestness, and sometimes with playful gaiety, replied to
her attacks. Though her manner varied, however, her determination never did.
Mr. Collins, meanwhile, was meditating in solitude on what had passed. He thought too
well of himself to comprehend on what motive his cousin could refuse him;
and though his pride was hurt, he suffered in no other way. His regard for her was quite imaginary;
and the possibility of her deserving her mother’s reproach prevented his feeling any regret.
While the family were in this confusion, Charlotte Lucas came to spend the day with them. She was met
in the vestibule by Lydia, who, flying to her, cried in a half whisper, “I am glad you are come,
for there is such fun here! What do you think has happened this morning? Mr. Collins has made an
offer to Lizzy, and she will not have him.” Charlotte had hardly time to answer
before they were joined by Kitty, who came to tell the same news; and no sooner had they entered the
breakfast-room, where Mrs. Bennet was alone, than she likewise began on the subject, calling
on Miss Lucas for her compassion, and entreating her to persuade her friend Lizzy to comply with
the wishes of her family. “Pray do, my dear Miss Lucas,” she added, in a melancholy tone; “for
nobody is on my side, nobody takes part with me; I am cruelly used, nobody feels for my poor nerves.”
Charlotte’s reply was spared by the entrance of Jane and Elizabeth.
“Ay, there she comes,” continued Mrs. Bennet, “looking as unconcerned as may be, and caring no
more for us than if we were at York, provided she can have her own way. But I tell you what, Miss
Lizzy, if you take it into your head to go on refusing every offer of marriage in this way, you
will never get a husband at all—and I am sure I do not know who is to maintain you when your father
is dead. I shall not be able to keep you—and so I warn you. I have done with you from this very day.
I told you in the library, you know, that I should never speak to you again, and you will find me as
good as my word. I have no pleasure in talking to undutiful children. Not that I have much pleasure,
indeed, in talking to anybody. People who suffer as I do from nervous complaints can
have no great inclination for talking. Nobody can tell what I suffer! But it is always so.
Those who do not complain are never pitied.” Her daughters listened in silence to this
effusion, sensible that any attempt to reason with or soothe her would
only increase the irritation. She talked on, therefore, without interruption from any of
them till they were joined by Mr. Collins, who entered with an air more stately than usual,
and on perceiving whom, she said to the girls,— “Now, I do insist upon it, that you, all of you,
hold your tongues, and let Mr. Collins and me have a little conversation together.”
Elizabeth passed quietly out of the room, Jane and Kitty followed, but Lydia stood her ground,
determined to hear all she could; and Charlotte, detained first by the civility of Mr. Collins,
whose inquiries after herself and all her family were very minute, and then by a little curiosity,
satisfied herself with walking to the window and pretending not to hear. In a doleful voice Mrs.
Bennet thus began the projected conversation:— “Oh, Mr. Collins!”
“My dear madam,” replied he, “let us be for ever silent on this point. Far be it from me,”
he presently continued, in a voice that marked his displeasure, “to resent the behaviour of
your daughter. Resignation to inevitable evils is the duty of us all: the peculiar duty of a
young man who has been so fortunate as I have been, in early preferment; and, I trust, I am
resigned. Perhaps not the less so from feeling a doubt of my positive happiness had my fair
cousin honoured me with her hand; for I have often observed, that resignation is never so perfect as
when the blessing denied begins to lose somewhat of its value in our estimation. You will not,
I hope, consider me as showing any disrespect to your family, my dear madam, by thus withdrawing
my pretensions to your daughter’s favour, without having paid yourself and Mr. Bennet
the compliment of requesting you to interpose your authority in my behalf. My conduct may, I fear,
be objectionable in having accepted my dismission from your daughter’s lips instead of your own;
but we are all liable to error. I have certainly meant well through the whole affair. My object has
been to secure an amiable companion for myself, with due consideration for the advantage of all
your family; and if my manner has been at all reprehensible, I here beg leave to apologize.”
CHAPTER XXI.
THE discussion of Mr. Collins’s offer was now nearly at an end, and Elizabeth had only to
suffer from the uncomfortable feelings necessarily attending it, and occasionally from some peevish
allusion of her mother. As for the gentleman himself, his feelings were chiefly expressed,
not by embarrassment or dejection, or by trying to avoid her, but by stiffness of manner and
resentful silence. He scarcely ever spoke to her; and the assiduous attentions which he had been so
sensible of himself were transferred for the rest of the day to Miss Lucas, whose civility
in listening to him was a seasonable relief to them all, and especially to her friend.
The morrow produced no abatement of Mrs. Bennet’s ill humour or ill health. Mr. Collins was also
in the same state of angry pride. Elizabeth had hoped that his resentment might shorten his visit,
but his plan did not appear in the least affected by it. He was always to have gone on Saturday,
and to Saturday he still meant to stay. After breakfast, the girls walked to Meryton,
to inquire if Mr. Wickham were returned, and to lament over his absence from the Netherfield
ball. He joined them on their entering the town, and attended them to their aunt’s,
where his regret and vexation and the concern of everybody were well talked over. To Elizabeth,
however, he voluntarily acknowledged that the necessity of his absence had been self-imposed.
“I found,” said he, “as the time drew near, that I had better not meet Mr.
Darcy;—that to be in the same room, the same party with him for so many hours together,
might be more than I could bear, and that scenes might arise unpleasant to more than myself.”
She highly approved his forbearance; and they had leisure for a full discussion of it,
and for all the commendations which they civilly bestowed on each other, as Wickham and another
officer walked back with them to Longbourn, and during the walk he particularly attended to her.
His accompanying them was a double advantage: she felt all the compliment it offered to herself;
and it was most acceptable as an occasion of introducing him to her father and mother.
to Miss Bennet; it came from Netherfield, and was opened immediately. The envelope contained
a sheet of elegant, little, hot-pressed paper, well covered with a lady’s fair, flowing hand;
and Elizabeth saw her sister’s countenance change as she read it, and saw her dwelling intently on
some particular passages. Jane recollected herself soon; and putting the letter away, tried to join,
with her usual cheerfulness, in the general conversation: but Elizabeth felt an anxiety on
the subject which drew off her attention even from Wickham; and no sooner had he and his companion
taken leave, than a glance from Jane invited her to follow her upstairs. When they had gained
their own room, Jane, taking out her letter, said, “This is from Caroline Bingley: what it
contains has surprised me a good deal. The whole party have left Netherfield by this time, and are
on their way to town; and without any intention of coming back again. You shall hear what she says.”
She then read the first sentence aloud, which comprised the information of their having just
resolved to follow their brother to town directly, and of their meaning to dine that day in Grosvenor
Street, where Mr. Hurst had a house. The next was in these words:—“‘I do not pretend to regret
anything I shall leave in Hertfordshire except your society, my dearest friend; but we will hope,
at some future period, to enjoy many returns of that delightful intercourse we have known,
and in the meanwhile may lessen the pain of separation by a very frequent and most unreserved
correspondence. I depend on you for that.’” To these high-flown expressions Elizabeth listened
with all the insensibility of distrust; and though the suddenness of their removal surprised her,
she saw nothing in it really to lament: it was not to be supposed that their absence from
Netherfield would prevent Mr. Bingley’s being there; and as to the loss of their society,
she was persuaded that Jane must soon cease to regard it in the enjoyment of his.
“It is unlucky,” said she, after a short pause, “that you should not be able to see your friends
before they leave the country. But may we not hope that the period of future happiness,
to which Miss Bingley looks forward, may arrive earlier than she is aware,
and that the delightful intercourse you have known as friends will be renewed with yet
greater satisfaction as sisters? Mr. Bingley will not be detained in London by them.”
“Caroline decidedly says that none of the party will return into Hertfordshire
this winter. I will read it to you. “‘When my brother left us yesterday,
he imagined that the business which took him to London might be concluded in three or four days;
but as we are certain it cannot be so, and at the same time convinced that when Charles gets to
town he will be in no hurry to leave it again, we have determined on following him thither,
that he may not be obliged to spend his vacant hours in a comfortless hotel. Many of
my acquaintance are already there for the winter: I wish I could hear that you, my dearest friend,
had any intention of making one in the crowd, but of that I despair. I sincerely hope your Christmas
in Hertfordshire may abound in the gaieties which that season generally brings, and that your beaux
will be so numerous as to prevent your feeling the loss of the three of whom we shall deprive you.’
“It is evident by this,” added Jane, “that he comes back no more this winter.”
“It is only evident that Miss Bingley does not mean he should.”
“Why will you think so? It must be his own doing; he is his own master. But you do not know all. I
will read you the passage which particularly hurts me. I will have no reserves from you.
‘Mr. Darcy is impatient to see his sister; and to confess the truth, we are scarcely
less eager to meet her again. I really do not think Georgiana Darcy has her equal for beauty,
elegance, and accomplishments; and the affection she inspires in Louisa and myself is heightened
into something still more interesting from the hope we dare to entertain of her being hereafter
our sister. I do not know whether I ever before mentioned to you my feelings on this subject,
but I will not leave the country without confiding them, and I trust you will not
esteem them unreasonable. My brother admires her greatly already; he will have frequent opportunity
now of seeing her on the most intimate footing; her relations all wish the connection as much
as his own; and a sister’s partiality is not misleading me, I think, when I call Charles
most capable of engaging any woman’s heart. With all these circumstances to favour an attachment,
and nothing to prevent it, am I wrong, my dearest Jane, in indulging the hope of an
event which will secure the happiness of so many?’ What think you of this sentence,
my dear Lizzy?” said Jane, as she finished it. “Is it not clear enough? Does it not expressly declare
that Caroline neither expects nor wishes me to be her sister; that she is perfectly convinced
of her brother’s indifference; and that if she suspects the nature of my feelings for him she
means (most kindly!) to put me on my guard. Can there be any other opinion on the subject?”
“Yes, there can; for mine is totally different. Will you hear it?”
“Most willingly.” “You shall have it in a few words. Miss Bingley
sees that her brother is in love with you and wants him to marry Miss Darcy. She follows him to
town in the hope of keeping him there, and tries to persuade you that he does not care about you.”
Jane shook her head. “Indeed, Jane, you ought to believe me.
No one who has ever seen you together can doubt his affection; Miss Bingley, I am sure, cannot:
she is not such a simpleton. Could she have seen half as much love in Mr. Darcy for herself,
she would have ordered her wedding clothes. But the case is this:—we are not rich enough or grand
enough for them; and she is the more anxious to get Miss Darcy for her brother, from the notion
that when there has been one inter-marriage, she may have less trouble in achieving a second;
in which there is certainly some ingenuity, and I dare say it would succeed if Miss de Bourgh were
out of the way. But, my dearest Jane, you cannot seriously imagine that, because Miss Bingley tells
you her brother greatly admires Miss Darcy, he is in the smallest degree less sensible of your merit
than when he took leave of you on Tuesday; or that it will be in her power to persuade him that,
instead of being in love with you, he is very much in love with her friend.”
“If we thought alike of Miss Bingley,” replied Jane, “your representation of all this might
make me quite easy. But I know the foundation is unjust. Caroline is incapable of wilfully
deceiving anyone; and all that I can hope in this case is, that she is deceived herself.”
“That is right. You could not have started a more happy idea,
since you will not take comfort in mine: believe her to be deceived,
by all means. You have now done your duty by her, and must fret no longer.”
“But, my dear sister, can I be happy, even supposing the best,
in accepting a man whose sisters and friends are all wishing him to marry elsewhere?”
“You must decide for yourself,” said Elizabeth; “and if, upon mature deliberation, you find that
the misery of disobliging his two sisters is more than equivalent to the happiness of being his
wife, I advise you, by all means, to refuse him.” “How can you talk so?” said Jane, faintly smiling;
“you must know, that, though I should be exceedingly grieved at their disapprobation,
I could not hesitate.” “I did not think you would;
and that being the case, I cannot consider your situation with much compassion.”
“But if he returns no more this winter, my choice will never be required. A thousand
things may arise in six months.” The idea of his returning no more
Elizabeth treated with the utmost contempt. It appeared to her merely the suggestion of
Caroline’s interested wishes; and she could not for a moment suppose that those wishes,
however openly or artfully spoken, could influence a young man so totally independent of everyone.
She represented to her sister, as forcibly as possible, what she felt on the subject,
and had soon the pleasure of seeing its happy effect. Jane’s temper was not desponding;
and she was gradually led to hope, though the diffidence of affection sometimes
overcame the hope, that Bingley would return to Netherfield, and answer every wish of her heart.
They agreed that Mrs. Bennet should only hear of the departure of the family, without being alarmed
on the score of the gentleman’s conduct; but even this partial communication gave her a great deal
of concern, and she bewailed it as exceedingly unlucky that the ladies should happen to go
away just as they were all getting so intimate together. After lamenting it, however, at some
length, she had the consolation of thinking that Mr. Bingley would be soon down again, and soon
dining at Longbourn; and the conclusion of all was the comfortable declaration, that, though
he had been invited only to a family dinner, she would take care to have two full courses.
CHAPTER XXII.